Okay, so let's talk about three-point
estimating now.
And three-point estimating is one of the
estimating methods,
right, for schedule and cost.
And this is primarily used for predictive
projects, right?
This will not be for agile projects.
Okay.
Now, there are two types of three-point
estimating.
You have something called the triangular
distribution, which is a straight average,
right?
The triangular distribution is a straight
average.
then there's another one on the next slide
called the beta distribution or the pert
which is a weighted average all right so
one is a straight average one is a
weighted average all right so let's go
back to the previous slide and let me just
briefly talk about the straight average
and it's a straight average of three
points right three numbers those numbers
or those points happen to be called
optimistic most likely pessimistic right
and how do you get an average of three
numbers right well you add
them up and you divide by three i
mean that's what an average
is right so it's nice and simple.
They give you the three numbers,
optimistic, most likely pessimistic, right?
You add them up, divide
by three, there's your
triangular distribution
or your straight average.
And of course, because it's so nice and
simple, the chance of you getting a
question on that and the exam is not very
high, right?
It's less likely to appear on the exam,
right?
But it can appear, right?
More than likely, though, you'll get a
question on the beta distribution,
right, which is a weighted average.
And again, it's a weighted average,
right?
Also known as a pert.
All right, so let's talk about this
formula in a bit more detail.
Now, PERD stands for program, evaluation,
and review technique.
And it's a weighted average.
Not a straight average, a weighted
average.
And it's also known as an expected
activity duration.
And you see the same
form in cost as well, in which
case it will be called
an expected activity cost.
Now, the formula for Pert, then,
is this here.
Optimistic plus four times most likely
plus pessimistic divided by six.
Remember, this is a weighted average.
It's a weighted average.
And what we're doing here is we are
weighting our most likely by four.
So it's optimistic plus four times most
likely even pessimistic divided by six.
Now, you don't need to know why your most
likely is weighted by four.
You just need to know that that is a case.
And the reason why
it's divided by six though
is because there are six data points now.
You've got four most likely than
optimistic and a pessimistic, that's six.
That's why you divide it by six.
Alright, so let's look at how you actually
use it.
Now typically then, this is a typical type
of question that you
could get on the exam.
So this says the activity should take 16
days, however, if things go well,
it might only take 10 days, if things go
badly, it might end up taking 34 days.
Right.
So they give you these three numbers.
So these three numbers then, activity
should take 16 days.
That's my most likely figure.
If things go well, it might only take 10
days.
That's my optimistic figure.
If things go badly, you might end up
taking 34 days.
Pessimistically, it might take 34.
That's my pessimistic figure.
In the exam, they will always give you
these three numbers.
And then, in order to get
the pert estimate, you'll
literally just add them
into the hurt formula, right?
Just basically plug the numbers in.
Right.
So this is a formula, optimistic,
plus four times most likely, plus
pessimistic divide by six, plug the
numbers in, right?
So the optimistic figure is 10, pessimistic
figure is 34, most likely 16, right?
And you're waiting our most likely by
four, so four times 16, and divide by six,
you get 18 days.
Now, what do we do with this 18 days.
I mean, why do we have, I
mean, we have these three
figures, what we're trying to
do with these three figures?
Basically, what we're trying
to do is come up with some
kind of range or some kind
of confidence range, right?
So we don't just basically set 18 days
aside, right, as our timeline,
right, because there could be so much
variation.
Remember, we're coming up with a range,
right?
Just said we're coming up with a
confidence range.
And so in order to come up with a
confidence range, next thing we have to
do, now is calculate something called
standard deviation.
Now, I'm sure some of you have spent
entire college semesters in standard
deviation, and some of you may have no
idea what standard deviation is.
I will literally just tell you what you
need to know for the PMP exam.
You don't need to know
a huge amount of detail,
you just need to know
the very, very basics.
Now, standard deviation
is a measure of precision,
and it's denoted by this
symbol a sigma, right?
So this symbol is called sigma.
Sigma and standard deviation basically
mean the same thing.
Now, it's a measure of precision.
There's various different ways of
calculating standard deviation,
but for the purpose of the P&P exam,
this is a formula that you need to know.
It's pessimistic minus optimistic,
divided by six.
It's the same pessimistic and optimistic
figures, right?
Same figures as what we had before,
right?
So most likely were 16, optimistic is 10,
pessimistic is 34.
But this one does not use most likely.
So these figures were from the previous
slide, right?
We calculated the pert of 18 days.
That was calculated from the previous
slide.
So in order to get the standard deviation,
just plug the numbers in, right?
So the pessimistic
figure is 34, optimistic
is 10, 34 minus 10
divided by 6, so we get 4.
So a standard deviation then is 4 days.
Now what do we do with this?
Well, we're trying to come up with a
range.
So we calculated the pert of 18 days from
the previous slide.
That is the average, remember.
That is the expected duration,
expected activity duration.
That is the mean, the pert of mean.
It's a weighted mean, but it's a mean.
So in order to come up with a range,
we will take our pert, right, this 18
days, and plus the standard
deviation to get an upper
range and minus a standard
deviation to get a lower range.
range, right?
So we've got the 18, 18 days, plus
standard deviation, 18 plus 4,
which is 22, and then 18 minus 4,
which is 14.
So that is our standard deviation range.
Now, I am going to expand on this a little
bit more.
I'm going to expand on standard deviation
a little bit more.
And for this, we need this, we need to, I
need to explain using
this little graph here.
Now, first of all, though, standard
deviation involves percentages.
So you need to know these percentages.
You need to know that 1 sigma is 68.26%.
2 sigma is 95.46%.
3 sigma 99.73, 6 sigma, 99.997%.
All right, so you need to memorize these
percentages.
Make sure you know these percentages.
Now, what this graph is showing very
briefly, right?
This is a normal distribution of a
population.
Right.
And straight down the middle, you've got
the mean, denoted by this symbol,
mu.
34.1% of the population, either side of
the mean add up to 68.2%.
Right.
And there's always rounding errors,
though.
Don't worry about the rounding errors.
But that adds up to 68% or 68.2%.
That represents a range of one standard
deviation.
Add on another 13.6% either.
side of the mean, that entire population
adds up to 95.46% of the population,
and that represents a range of two
standard deviations.
Add on another 2.1% either side
of the mean, that adds up to 99.
73% of the population, which
is three standard deviations.
And they're not drawn to scale,
but add on another 0.1% either side,
and that adds up to
99.997% of the population,
and that is a range of basically 6-sigma.
Now, notice, these sigma levels are all
equal distance apart, right?
So a 6-sigma would really be all the way
out here, somewhere.
Right, there's also 4-and-5 sigma, which
you do not need to know for the exam.
So we have a formula for
standard deviation, right,
which is pessimistic minus
optimistic divided by 6.
But there are 6 standard deviation levels,
so which one does this refer to?
this refers to one sigma, one standard
deviation.
Now, when it comes to schedule management
and cost, right, we do these both in
schedule and cost, these percentages here
do not represent populations, they
represent confidence levels, right,
or represent probabilities.
So at one sigma, we'll say there's a 68%
probability of an event happening,
or we are 68% confident or 68.26%
confident of an event happening.
2 Sigma will be 95.46% confidence,
right?
Or we're at 95.46% confidence level.
So in the previous slide then, previous
page, we calculated the range, right?
Remember, the pert was 18, standard
deviation was 4.
So we calculated this range of 22 and 14,
18 plus 4, 18 minus 4.
using this formula standard deviation
remember that is one sigma one standard
deviation so this range that we've
calculated is to a range of 68% one sigma
68% or 68.26% so this is a 68% confidence
range right now if this was on our graph
then right those numbers on our graph
would basically look like this right
straight down the
middle is a mean right and
And our mean is our
pert, which is 18 days.
One standard deviation, we've calculated
as 4.
So 18 plus 4, 18 minus 4.
That's our standard deviation range.
And that is our 68.26% confidence range.
Now, 68% is not very confident.
So maybe we want to go with a 95%
confidence.
So what's our 95% confidence then?
95% confidence is two standard deviations,
2 sigma.
If one sigma is 4, then 2 sigma is
literally going to be 2 times 4.
Remember, these are all equal distance
apart.
So one standard deviation
is 4, right, therefore
2 standard deviations is going to be 8.
So the range then at 95% confidence will
be 18 plus 8, 18 minus 8.
right so 26 and 10 that's our 95%
confidence if we were calculating to a
99.73% confidence then it would literally
again be right 99.73 is three standard
deviations right if one standard deviation
is four that means three standard
deviations three times four which is 12 so
it would be 18 plus 12 18 minus 12 right
that would be a range to a 99.73 percent
confidence.
And that really is about as much as what
you need for the PMP exam regarding
standard deviation and perks.
That's really about as much as what you
need.
Now, there is one more
formula I want to mention, or one
more term, and that is
something called activity variance.
And all you need to
know regarding activity
variance is that standard
deviation squared.
And our standard deviation we've
calculated is a four, right?
So four squared then is 16.
Right.
So that's That's really
all you need to know,
say the activity variance then will be 16.
You don't necessarily need to know how to
use it in any detail, right?
Just in case they ask you, what calculate
activity variance?
It's standard deviation squared.
Okay.
All right, so if I just quickly go back to
the formula pages, right?
So we just did the beta distribution,
which is a weighted average, right?
And we went through this formula,
right?
The mean, the pert, right, and the
standard deviation, and the variance.
which is a standard deviation squared.
So remember, this could also be called the
expected duration,
expected activity duration.
Now remember, the other one then is a
triangular distribution,
less likely to appear.
But if they do, right,
the mean is optimistic,
most likely pessimistic divided by three.
If they ask you to calculate standard
deviation, using the triangular
distribution, then again, it's going to be
divided by three, by 6.
Now, which one do you use on the exam?
Well, if it doesn't tell you which one to
use, the beta distribution is the default,
right?
The pert is the default.
If it just says use a
three-point estimating,
then use the beta
distribution, use the pert.